Harrison Trice Papers /3010
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Harrison Trice Papers
1959-1972
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Trice, Harrison M.
/3010
2.5 cubic feet
2.5 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
Drug user and alcoholic interview notes.
3070053
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, March 09, 2015
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, October 11, 2022
Biographical / Historical
Harrison Miller Trice (May 25, 1920 December 5, 1994)
Harrison Miller Trice was Professor Emeritus in the Department of Organizational Behavior at the School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University, where he had been a member of the faculty since 1955. Professor Trice's major contribution to his discipline has been the integration of the study of alcohol and drugs with the study of the workplace. More than any other social scientist, he was responsible for integrating occupational and organizational sociology with the study of alcohol and drugs.
His courses on occupational culture, deviance in the workplace, and employee assistance programs were always popular. Until his retirement, he conducted a large course in which each student was required to carry out a specific field study. Among the most popular of these studies were those concerned with alcohol and drugs. While committed to research and public policy, Harrison Trice was also committed to teaching.
Prior to his retirement from teaching in 1991, Professor Trice also played the pivotal role in securing an endowment to establish Cornell's R. Brinkley Smithers Institute for Alcohol-Related Workplace Studies at the School of Industrial and Labor Relations. After his retirement, he kept up an active research program, completing two books in 1993 on organizational culture-The Cultures of Work Organizations, co-authored with Professor Janice Beyer, and Occupational Subcultures in the Workplace. Both books have received great acclaim from reviewers. At the time of his death, he and Professor Paul Roman were revising Spirits and Demons at Work: Alcohol and Drugs on the Job, and he was co-editing with Professor Paul Steele a special issue of the Journal of Drug Issues on workplace programs for the prevention and treatment of alcohol and other drug problems.
In 1994, Professor Trice was the recipient of two awards which recognized his lifetime contributions to the field of alcohol and drug studies. In August, he received the Distinguished Career Award from the American Sociological Association's Drinking and Drugs Section. In November, he received an award from New York State's Office of Alcoholism and Substance Abuse Services for his many contributions to the area of employee assistance programs, particularly his efforts to deliver rigorous training and education programs to practitioners.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1945 as the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, the ILR School today is advancing the world of work through teaching, research and outreach. ILR's mission is to prepare leaders, inform national and international employment and labor policy, and improve working lives, but as the world of work evolves, the school's focus broadens to keep pace with that change. ILR studies many areas that shape the working world and contribute to an organization's success in a global economy. These include human resource management; labor-management relations; labor economics; organizational behavior; international and comparative labor; labor relations, labor law and history; conflict resolution; management development; diversity management; employment and disability; and social statistics. An ILR education is grounded in the social sciences. Students and faculty explore and gain an understanding of human behavior through the lens of the workplace. Students also learn how organizations work and how they fit into the larger society and economy. As a result, they acquire knowledge and skills that help them to solve problems on-the-job and to build and manage productive work relationships. An ILR education, for students and professionals, is practical and applied. ILR has more full-time faculty involved in teaching and research that spans the broad range of work and employment disciplines than any other educational institution of its kind. Its Martin P. Catherwood Library is regarded as the most comprehensive source of information in North America on work, employment and labor issues.
Scope and Contents
Trice was a pioneer in the study of industrial alcoholism and his papers are important for this. This collection consists of extensive notes from interviews with drug users and alcoholics.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4164: Harrison M. Trice Additional Papers /4254: Harrison Trice Additional Books
Alcoholism -- Study and teaching; Trice, Harrison Miller,1920-; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Faculty.
3070053
- Trice-Scully Vol. 2: 8.1-9.4, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Trice-Scully Vol. 2: 10.1-11.4, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Trice-Scully Vol. 2: 12.1 - 13.4, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Daily Sun, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Drug Information, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Drug Culture Study, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Maps, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Index of Musicians (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Scope and Contents
  3 small index card boxes
- Index of Books (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Index of Authors, Magazines, Comix, Actors, Television, Movies (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Trice-Scully Vol. 1: 1.1 - 1.4 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Trice-Scully Vol. 1: 2.1-3.4 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Trice-Scully Vol. 1: 4.1-5.4 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Trice-Scully Vol. 1: 6.1-7.4 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Change, Fired Absenteeism (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Work Performance (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Job Descriptions (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Role of Alcohol in Performing Job (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Accidents (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Drinking Millew of Job Morning Drinking (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Drinking During Working Hours Perfectionism (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Job Freedom (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Folder-B (IBM - Cross tabulations) (Box 2, Folder 13)
- IBM Type 101 Electronic Statistical Machine (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Drinking Group Participation (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Tables, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- General Hypotheses (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Scully-424C plx. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Routine (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Interview (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Inventory of the Job Experience (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Routine Morning Drinking (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Appearance (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Work Performance Job Efficiency (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Cover-up (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Job Freedom Turnover (Box 3, Folder 10)
- High Status Job Experience (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Text (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Inventory of Job Experience - Numbered (Box 3, Folder 13)
- ASPA Cornell Project, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)